<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en"><head>
<meta charset="utf-8" />
<meta http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible" content="IE=edge" />
<meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1" />
<title>EIP-2981: NFT Royalty Standard</title>
<meta property="og:title" content="EIP-2981: NFT Royalty Standard" />
<meta name="description" content="" />
<meta property="og:description" content="" />
<meta name="twitter:description" content="" />
<meta name="generator" content="Jekyll" />
<meta property="og:locale" content="en_US" />
<link rel="canonical" href="https://eips.ethereum.org/EIPS/eip-2981" />
<meta property="og:url" content="https://eips.ethereum.org/EIPS/eip-2981" />
<meta property="og:site_name" content="Ethereum Improvement Proposals" />
<meta name="twitter:card" content="summary" />
<meta name="twitter:site" content="@" />
<script type="application/ld+json">
    {
      "@type": "WebSite",
      "url": "https://eips.ethereum.org",
      "name": "Ethereum Improvement Proposals",
      "description": "Ethereum Improvement Proposals (EIPs) describe standards for the Ethereum platform, including core protocol specifications, client APIs, and contract standards.",
      "@context": "https://schema.org"
    }
  </script>
<link rel="stylesheet" href="/assets/css/style.css" /><link type="application/atom+xml" rel="alternate" href="https://eips.ethereum.org/feed.xml" title="Ethereum Improvement Proposals" /><script async src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.6/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML" integrity="sha256-nlrDrBTHxJJlDDX22AS33xYI1OJHnGMDhiYMSe2U0e0=" crossorigin="anonymous"></script>
</head>
<body><header class="site-header" role="banner">
<div class="wrapper"><a class="site-title" rel="author" href="/">Ethereum Improvement Proposals</a><nav class="site-nav">
<input type="checkbox" id="nav-trigger" class="nav-trigger" />
<label for="nav-trigger">
<span class="menu-icon">
<svg viewBox="0 0 18 15" width="18px" height="15px">
<path d="M18,1.484c0,0.82-0.665,1.484-1.484,1.484H1.484C0.665,2.969,0,2.304,0,1.484l0,0C0,0.665,0.665,0,1.484,0 h15.032C17.335,0,18,0.665,18,1.484L18,1.484z M18,7.516C18,8.335,17.335,9,16.516,9H1.484C0.665,9,0,8.335,0,7.516l0,0 c0-0.82,0.665-1.484,1.484-1.484h15.032C17.335,6.031,18,6.696,18,7.516L18,7.516z M18,13.516C18,14.335,17.335,15,16.516,15H1.484 C0.665,15,0,14.335,0,13.516l0,0c0-0.82,0.665-1.483,1.484-1.483h15.032C17.335,12.031,18,12.695,18,13.516L18,13.516z" />
</svg>
</span>
</label>
<div class="trigger"><a class="page-link" href="/all">All</a><a class="page-link" href="/core">Core</a><a class="page-link" href="/networking">Networking</a><a class="page-link" href="/interface">Interface</a><a class="page-link" href="/erc">ERC</a><a class="page-link" href="/meta">Meta</a><a class="page-link" href="/informational">Informational</a></div>
</nav></div>
</header>
<main class="page-content" aria-label="Content">
<div class="wrapper">
<div class="home">
<h1 class="page-heading">
EIP-2981: NFT Royalty Standard
<a href="https://github.com/ethereum/EIPs/blob/master/EIPS/eip-2981.md"><svg role="img" aria-label="Source" xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="14" height="16" viewBox="0 0 14 16"><title>Source</title><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M9.5 3L8 4.5 11.5 8 8 11.5 9.5 13 14 8 9.5 3zm-5 0L0 8l4.5 5L6 11.5 2.5 8 6 4.5 4.5 3z" /></svg></a>
</h1>
<h3></h3>
<table>
<tr><th>Author</th><td><a href="https://github.com/vexycats">Zach Burks</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jamesmorgan">James Morgan</a>, <a href="https://github.com/blmalone">Blaine Malone</a>, <a href="https://github.com/seibelj">James Seibel</a></td></tr>
<tr><th>Discussions-To</th><td><a href="https://github.com/ethereum/EIPs/issues/2907">https://github.com/ethereum/EIPs/issues/2907</a></td></tr>
<tr><th>Status</th><td>Final
</td></tr>
<tr><th>Type</th><td>Standards Track</td></tr>
<tr><th>Category</th><td>ERC</td></tr>
<tr><th>Created</th><td>2020-09-15</td></tr>
<tr><th>Requires</th><td>
<a href="eip-165">165</a>
</td></tr>
</table>
<div class="toc">
<h2>Table of Contents</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="#simple-summary">Simple Summary</a></li>
<li><a href="#abstract">Abstract</a></li>
<li><a href="#motivation">Motivation</a></li>
<li><a href="#specification">Specification</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#examples">Examples</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#rationale">Rationale</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#optional-royalty-payments">Optional royalty payments</a></li>
<li><a href="#simple-royalty-payments-to-a-single-address">Simple royalty payments to a single address</a></li>
<li><a href="#royalty-payment-percentage-calculation">Royalty payment percentage calculation</a></li>
<li><a href="#unit-less-royalty-payment-across-all-marketplaces-both-on-chain-and-off-chain">Unit-less royalty payment across all marketplaces, both on-chain and off-chain</a></li>
<li><a href="#universal-royalty-payments">Universal Royalty Payments</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#backwards-compatibility">Backwards Compatibility</a></li>
<li><a href="#security-considerations">Security Considerations</a></li>
<li><a href="#copyright">Copyright</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2 id="simple-summary">
<a href="#simple-summary" class="anchor-link"></a> Simple Summary
</h2>
<p>A standardized way to retrieve royalty payment information for non-fungible tokens (NFTs) to enable universal support for royalty payments across all NFT marketplaces and ecosystem participants.</p>
<h2 id="abstract">
<a href="#abstract" class="anchor-link"></a> Abstract
</h2>
<p>This standard allows contracts, such as NFTs that support <a href="/EIPS/eip-721">ERC-721</a> and <a href="/EIPS/eip-1155">ERC-1155</a> interfaces, to signal a royalty amount to be paid to the NFT creator or rights holder every time the NFT is sold or re-sold. This is intended for NFT marketplaces that want to support the ongoing funding of artists and other NFT creators. The royalty payment must be voluntary, as transfer mechanisms such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">transferFrom()</code> include NFT transfers between wallets, and executing them does not always imply a sale occurred. Marketplaces and individuals implement this standard by retrieving the royalty payment information with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code>, which specifies how much to pay to which address for a given sale price. The exact mechanism for paying and notifying the recipient will be defined in future EIPs. This ERC should be considered a minimal, gas-efficient building block for further innovation in NFT royalty payments.</p>
<h2 id="motivation">
<a href="#motivation" class="anchor-link"></a> Motivation
</h2>
<p>There are many marketplaces for NFTs with multiple unique royalty payment implementations that are not easily compatible or usable by other marketplaces. Just like the early days of ERC-20 tokens, NFT marketplace smart contracts are varied by ecosystem and not standardized. This EIP enables all marketplaces to retrieve royalty payment information for a given NFT. This enables accurate royalty payments regardless of which marketplace the NFT is sold or re-sold at.</p>
<p>Many of the largest NFT marketplaces have implemented bespoke royalty payment solutions that are incompatible with other marketplaces. This standard implements standardized royalty information retrieval that can be accepted across any type of NFT marketplace. This minimalist proposal only provides a mechanism to fetch the royalty amount and recipient. The actual funds transfer is something which the marketplace should execute.</p>
<p>This standard allows NFTs that support <a href="/EIPS/eip-721">ERC-721</a> and <a href="/EIPS/eip-1155">ERC-1155</a> interfaces, to have a standardized way of signalling royalty information. More specifically, these contracts can now calculate a royalty amount to provide to the rightful recipient.</p>
<p>Royalty amounts are always a percentage of the sale price. If a marketplace chooses <em>not</em> to implement this EIP, then no funds will be paid for secondary sales. It is believed that the NFT marketplace ecosystem will voluntarily implement this royalty payment standard; in a bid to provide ongoing funding for artists/creators. NFT buyers will assess the royalty payment as a factor when making NFT purchasing decisions.</p>
<p>Without an agreed royalty payment standard, the NFT ecosystem will lack an effective means to collect royalties across all marketplaces and artists and other creators will not receive ongoing funding. This will hamper the growth and adoption of NFTs and demotivate NFT creators from minting new and innovative tokens.</p>
<p>Enabling all NFT marketplaces to unify on a single royalty payment standard will benefit the entire NFT ecosystem.</p>
<p>While this standard focuses on NFTs and compatibility with the ERC-721 and ERC-1155 standards, EIP-2981 does not require compatibility with ERC-721 and ERC-1155 standards. Any other contract could integrate with EIP-2981 to return royalty payment information. ERC-2981 is, therefore, a universal royalty standard for many asset types.</p>
<p>At a glance, here’s an example conversation summarizing NFT royalty payments today:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Artist</strong>: “Do you support royalty payments on your platform?” <br />
<strong>Marketplace</strong>: “Yes we have royalty payments, but if your NFT is sold on another marketplace then we cannot enforce this payment.” <br />
<strong>Artist</strong>: “What about other marketplaces that support royalties, don’t you share my royalty information to make this work?” <br />
<strong>Marketplace</strong>: “No, we do not share royalty information.”</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="specification">
<a href="#specification" class="anchor-link"></a> Specification
</h2>
<p>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL
NOT”, “SHOULD”, “SHOULD NOT”, “RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and
“OPTIONAL” in this document are to be interpreted as described in
RFC 2119.</p>
<p><strong>ERC-721 and ERC-1155 compliant contracts MAY implement this ERC for royalties to provide a standard method of specifying royalty payment information.</strong></p>
<p>Marketplaces that support this standard <strong>SHOULD</strong> implement some method of transferring royalties to the royalty recipient. Standards for the actual transfer and notification of funds will be specified in future EIPs.</p>
<p>Marketplaces <strong>MUST</strong> pay the royalty in the same unit of exchange as that of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> passed to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code>. This is equivalent to saying that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> parameter and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> return value <strong>MUST</strong> be denominated in the same monetary unit. For example, if the sale price is in ETH, then the royalty payment must also be paid in ETH, and if the sale price is in USDC, then the royalty payment must also be paid in USDC.</p>
<p>Implementers of this standard <strong>MUST</strong> calculate a percentage of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> when calculating the royalty amount. Subsequent invocations of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code> <strong>MAY</strong> return a different <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code>. Though there are some important considerations for implementers if they choose to perform different percentage calculations between <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code> invocations.</p>
<p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code> function is not aware of the unit of exchange for the sale and royalty payment. With that in mind, implementers <strong>MUST NOT</strong> return a fixed/constant <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code>, wherein they’re ignoring the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code>. For the same reason, implementers <strong>MUST NOT</strong> determine the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> based on comparing the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> with constant numbers. In both cases, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code> function makes assumptions on the unit of exchange, which <strong>MUST</strong> be avoided.</p>
<p>The percentage value used must be independent of the sale price for reasons previously mentioned (i.e. if the percentage value 10%, then 10% <strong>MUST</strong> apply whether <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> is 10, 10000 or 1234567890). If the royalty fee calculation results in a remainder, implementers <strong>MAY</strong> round up or round down to the nearest integer. For example, if the royalty fee is 10% and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> is 999, the implementer can return either 99 or 100 for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code>, both are valid.</p>
<p>The implementer <strong>MAY</strong> choose to change the percentage value based on other predictable variables that do not make assumptions about the unit of exchange. For example, the percentage value may drop linearly over time. An approach like this <strong>SHOULD NOT</strong> be based on variables that are unpredictable like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">block.timestamp</code>, but instead on other more predictable state changes. One more reasonable approach <strong>MAY</strong> use the number of transfers of an NFT to decide which percentage value is used to calculate the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code>. The idea being that the percentage value could decrease after each transfer of the NFT. Another example could be using a different percentage value for each unique <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_tokenId</code>.</p>
<p>Marketplaces that support this standard <strong>SHOULD NOT</strong> send a zero-value transaction if the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> returned is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0</code>. This would waste gas and serves no useful purpose in this EIP.</p>
<p>Marketplaces that support this standard <strong>MUST</strong> pay royalties no matter where the sale occurred or in what currency, including on-chain sales, over-the-counter (OTC) sales and off-chain sales such as at auction houses. As royalty payments are voluntary, entities that respect this EIP must pay no matter where the sale occurred - a sale conducted outside of the blockchain is still a sale. The exact mechanism for paying and notifying the recipient will be defined in future EIPs.</p>
<p>Implementers of this standard <strong>MUST</strong> have all of the following functions:</p>
<div class="language-solidity highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">pragma</span> <span class="n">solidity</span> <span class="o">^</span><span class="mf">0.6</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="k">import</span> <span class="s">"./IERC165.sol"</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="c1">///
/// @dev Interface for the NFT Royalty Standard
///
</span><span class="k">interface</span> <span class="n">IERC2981</span> <span class="k">is</span> <span class="n">IERC165</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c1">/// ERC165 bytes to add to interface array - set in parent contract
</span>    <span class="c1">/// implementing this standard
</span>    <span class="c1">///
</span>    <span class="c1">/// bytes4(keccak256("royaltyInfo(uint256,uint256)")) == 0x2a55205a
</span>    <span class="c1">/// bytes4 private constant _INTERFACE_ID_ERC2981 = 0x2a55205a;
</span>    <span class="c1">/// _registerInterface(_INTERFACE_ID_ERC2981);
</span>
    <span class="c1">/// @notice Called with the sale price to determine how much royalty
</span>    <span class="c1">//          is owed and to whom.
</span>    <span class="c1">/// @param _tokenId - the NFT asset queried for royalty information
</span>    <span class="c1">/// @param _salePrice - the sale price of the NFT asset specified by _tokenId
</span>    <span class="c1">/// @return receiver - address of who should be sent the royalty payment
</span>    <span class="c1">/// @return royaltyAmount - the royalty payment amount for _salePrice
</span>    <span class="k">function</span> <span class="n">royaltyInfo</span><span class="p">(</span>
        <span class="kt">uint256</span> <span class="n">_tokenId</span><span class="p">,</span>
        <span class="kt">uint256</span> <span class="n">_salePrice</span>
    <span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">external</span> <span class="k">view</span> <span class="k">returns</span> <span class="p">(</span>
        <span class="kt">address</span> <span class="n">receiver</span><span class="p">,</span>
        <span class="kt">uint256</span> <span class="n">royaltyAmount</span>
    <span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="k">interface</span> <span class="n">IERC165</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c1">/// @notice Query if a contract implements an interface
</span>    <span class="c1">/// @param interfaceID The interface identifier, as specified in ERC-165
</span>    <span class="c1">/// @dev Interface identification is specified in ERC-165. This function
</span>    <span class="c1">///  uses less than 30,000 gas.
</span>    <span class="c1">/// @return `true` if the contract implements `interfaceID` and
</span>    <span class="c1">///  `interfaceID` is not 0xffffffff, `false` otherwise
</span>    <span class="k">function</span> <span class="n">supportsInterface</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">bytes4</span> <span class="n">interfaceID</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">external</span> <span class="k">view</span> <span class="k">returns</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">bool</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<h3 id="examples">
<a href="#examples" class="anchor-link"></a> Examples
</h3>
<p>This standard being used on an ERC-721 during deployment:</p>
<h4 id="deploying-an-erc-721-and-signaling-support-for-erc-2981">
<a href="#deploying-an-erc-721-and-signaling-support-for-erc-2981" class="anchor-link"></a> Deploying an ERC-721 and signaling support for ERC-2981
</h4>
<div class="language-solidity highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">constructor</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">string</span> <span class="k">memory</span> <span class="n">name</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">string</span> <span class="k">memory</span> <span class="n">symbol</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kt">string</span> <span class="k">memory</span> <span class="n">baseURI</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="n">_name</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">name</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="n">_symbol</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">symbol</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="n">_setBaseURI</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">baseURI</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="c1">// register the supported interfaces to conform to ERC721 via ERC165
</span>        <span class="n">_registerInterface</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_INTERFACE_ID_ERC721</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="n">_registerInterface</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_INTERFACE_ID_ERC721_METADATA</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="n">_registerInterface</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_INTERFACE_ID_ERC721_ENUMERABLE</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="c1">// Royalties interface
</span>        <span class="n">_registerInterface</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_INTERFACE_ID_ERC2981</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<h4 id="checking-if-the-nft-being-sold-on-your-marketplace-implemented-royalties">
<a href="#checking-if-the-nft-being-sold-on-your-marketplace-implemented-royalties" class="anchor-link"></a> Checking if the NFT being sold on your marketplace implemented royalties
</h4>
<div class="language-solidity highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kt">bytes4</span> <span class="k">private</span> <span class="k">constant</span> <span class="n">_INTERFACE_ID_ERC2981</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mh">0x2a55205a</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="k">function</span> <span class="n">checkRoyalties</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">address</span> <span class="n">_contract</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">internal</span> <span class="k">returns</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">bool</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">bool</span> <span class="n">success</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">IERC165</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_contract</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="n">supportsInterface</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">_INTERFACE_ID_ERC2981</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">success</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<h2 id="rationale">
<a href="#rationale" class="anchor-link"></a> Rationale
</h2>
<h3 id="optional-royalty-payments">
<a href="#optional-royalty-payments" class="anchor-link"></a> Optional royalty payments
</h3>
<p>It is impossible to know which NFT transfers are the result of sales, and which are merely wallets moving or consolidating their NFTs. Therefore, we cannot force every transfer function, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">transferFrom()</code> in ERC-721, to involve a royalty payment as not every transfer is a sale that would require such payment. We believe the NFT marketplace ecosystem will voluntarily implement this royalty payment standard to provide ongoing funding for artists/creators. NFT buyers will assess the royalty payment as a factor when making NFT purchasing decisions.</p>
<h3 id="simple-royalty-payments-to-a-single-address">
<a href="#simple-royalty-payments-to-a-single-address" class="anchor-link"></a> Simple royalty payments to a single address
</h3>
<p>This EIP does not specify the manner of payment to the royalty recipient. Furthermore, it is impossible to fully know and efficiently implement all possible types of royalty payments logic. With that said, it is on the royalty payment receiver to implement all additional complexity and logic for fee splitting, multiple receivers, taxes, accounting, etc. in their own receiving contract or off-chain processes. Attempting to do this as part of this standard, it would dramatically increase the implementation complexity, increase gas costs, and could not possibly cover every potential use-case. This ERC should be considered a minimal, gas-efficient building block for further innovation in NFT royalty payments. Future EIPs can specify more details regarding payment transfer and notification.</p>
<h3 id="royalty-payment-percentage-calculation">
<a href="#royalty-payment-percentage-calculation" class="anchor-link"></a> Royalty payment percentage calculation
</h3>
<p>This EIP mandates a percentage-based royalty fee model. It is likely that the most common case of percentage calculation will be where the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> is always calculated from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> using a fixed percent i.e. if the royalty fee is 10%, then a 10% royalty fee must apply whether <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_salePrice</code> is 10, 10000 or 1234567890.</p>
<p>As previously mentioned, implementers can get creative with this percentage-based calculation but there are some important caveats to consider. Mainly, ensuring that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code> function is not aware of the unit of exchange and that unpredictable variables are avoided in the percentage calculation. To follow up on the earlier <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">block.timestamp</code> example, there is some nuance which can be highlighted if the following events ensued:</p>
<ol>
<li>Marketplace sells NFT.</li>
<li>Marketplace delays <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">X</code> days before invoking <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code> and sending payment.</li>
<li>Marketplace receives <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Y</code> for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> which was significantly different from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> amount that would’ve been calculated <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">X</code> days prior if no delay had occurred.</li>
<li>Royalty recipient is dissatisfied with the delay from the marketplace and for this reason, they raise a dispute.</li>
</ol>
<p>Rather than returning a percentage and letting the marketplace calculate the royalty amount based on the sale price, a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> value is returned so there is no dispute with a marketplace over how much is owed for a given sale price. The royalty fee payer must pay the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyAmount</code> that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">royaltyInfo()</code> stipulates.</p>
<h3 id="unit-less-royalty-payment-across-all-marketplaces-both-on-chain-and-off-chain">
<a href="#unit-less-royalty-payment-across-all-marketplaces-both-on-chain-and-off-chain" class="anchor-link"></a> Unit-less royalty payment across all marketplaces, both on-chain and off-chain
</h3>
<p>This EIP does not specify a currency or token used for sales and royalty payments. The same percentage-based royalty fee must be paid regardless of what currency, or token was used in the sale, paid in the same currency or token. This applies to sales in any location including on-chain sales, over-the-counter (OTC) sales, and off-chain sales using fiat currency such as at auction houses. As royalty payments are voluntary, entities that respect this EIP must pay no matter where the sale occurred - a sale outside of the blockchain is still a sale. The exact mechanism for paying and notifying the recipient will be defined in future EIPs.</p>
<h3 id="universal-royalty-payments">
<a href="#universal-royalty-payments" class="anchor-link"></a> Universal Royalty Payments
</h3>
<p>Although designed specifically with NFTs in mind, this standard does not require that a contract implementing EIP-2981 is compatible with either ERC-721 or ERC-1155 standards. Any other contract could use this interface to return royalty payment information, provided that it is able to uniquely identify assets within the constraints of the interface. ERC-2981 is, therefore, a universal royalty standard for many other asset types.</p>
<h2 id="backwards-compatibility">
<a href="#backwards-compatibility" class="anchor-link"></a> Backwards Compatibility
</h2>
<p>This standard is compatible with current ERC-721 and ERC-1155 standards.</p>
<h2 id="security-considerations">
<a href="#security-considerations" class="anchor-link"></a> Security Considerations
</h2>
<p>There are no security considerations related directly to the implementation of this standard.</p>
<h2 id="copyright">
<a href="#copyright" class="anchor-link"></a> Copyright
</h2>
<p>Copyright and related rights waived via <a href="/LICENSE">CC0</a>.</p>
<h2>Citation</h2>
<p>Please cite this document as:</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/vexycats">Zach Burks</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jamesmorgan">James Morgan</a>, <a href="https://github.com/blmalone">Blaine Malone</a>, <a href="https://github.com/seibelj">James Seibel</a>, "EIP-2981: NFT Royalty Standard," <em>Ethereum Improvement Proposals</em>, no. 2981, September 2020. [Online serial]. Available: https://eips.ethereum.org/EIPS/eip-2981.</p>
</div>
<script type="application/ld+json">
  {
    "@context": "http://schema.org",
    "@type": "TechArticle",
    "headline": "EIP-2981: NFT Royalty Standard",
    "author": "Zach Burks (@vexycats), James Morgan (@jamesmorgan), Blaine Malone (@blmalone), James Seibel (@seibelj)",
    "name": "EIP-2981: NFT Royalty Standard",
    "dateCreated": "2020-09-15",
    "datePublished": "2020-09-15",

    "discussionUrl": "https://github.com/ethereum/EIPs/issues/2907",
    
    "inLanguage": "en-US",
    "license": "#copyright",
    "copyrightYear": "2020"
  }
</script>
</div>
</main><footer class="site-footer h-card">
<data class="u-url" href="/"></data>
<div class="wrapper">
<h2 class="footer-heading">Ethereum Improvement Proposals</h2>
<div class="footer-col-wrapper">
<div class="footer-col footer-col-1">
<ul class="contact-list">
<li class="p-name">Ethereum Improvement Proposals</li></ul>
</div>
<div class="footer-col footer-col-2"><ul class="social-media-list"><li><a href="https://github.com/ethereum/EIPs"><svg class="svg-icon"><use xlink:href="/assets/minima-social-icons.svg#github"></use></svg> <span class="username">ethereum/EIPs</span></a></li></ul>
</div>
<div class="footer-col footer-col-3">
<p>Ethereum Improvement Proposals (EIPs) describe standards for the Ethereum platform, including core protocol specifications, client APIs, and contract standards.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</footer>
</body>
</html>
